A Guide to the Bowers (John Z.) papers, Accession 2008:069 FA245
Rockefeller Archive Center
John Z. Bowers papers, Accession 2008:069
1951-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bowers, John Z.
Rockefeller Foundation
FA245
9.17 Cubic Feet 7 standard record storage boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Arrangement
Records remain as received.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the research files of John Z. Bowers including articles, manuscripts, notes, photocopies, and other background materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated to the RAC in 2008 by the Medical Center Archives of New York-Presbyterian/Weill Cornell.
Biographical / Historical
Historian and educator John Zimmerman Bowers served as president of the Josiah Macy Jr. Foundation of New York, which focuses its work in the areas of health and medicine. Prior to his service to the Macy Foundation, he was dean and professor of medical physics at the University of Utah and he also served the Ford Foundation primarily through work in India. After Bowers service to the Macy Foundation, he was a consultant for the Rockefeller Foundation for which he compiled a history of their health and natural-science programs in 1983.
Bowers authored or edited several major publications and essays including but not necessarily limited to: "Western Medical Pioneers in Feudal Japan" (1970), "When the Twain Meet: The Rise of Western Medicine in Japan" (1981), "Advances in American Medicine" and "Science and Medicine in Twentieth-Century China" (1989).
- Medicine in Japan, 1951-1979; 1
  - Medicine in Japan, 1951-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1-57)
    Scope and Contents
    Articles, manuscripts and images, by Bowers and others, pertaining to the history of medicine in Japan
  - Medicine in Japan, 1951-1979 (Box 2, Folder 58-105)
    Articles and manuscripts (by others) on the history of medicine in Japan and the Philippines
  - Medicine in Japan, 1955-1978 (Box 3, Folder 106-196)
    Articles (by others) on individuals related to the history of medicine in Japan, including anthropologist Erwin von Balz
- History of Medical Schools, 1973-1978; 2
  - History of Medical Schools, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 197-223)
    Research notes (by Bowers) and articles (by others) on the history of medicine in India, Paris, Salerno and Vienna. Includes drafts of the manuscript "Great Medical Schools".
  - History of Medical Schools, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 224-255)
    Manuscripts (by Bowers) and articles (by others) pertaining to the history of medicine in Bologna, Edinburgh, Germany, Leyden, Montpellier and Padia.
- Medicine in the United States, 1955-1977; 3
  - Medicine in the United States, 1955-1977 (Box 6, Folder 256-302)
    Articles (by others) on topics pertaining to medicine in the United States.
- History of Smallpox, 1969-1980; 4
  - History of Smallpox, 1969-1980 (Box 7, Folder 303-341)
    Research notes, manuscripts (by Bowers) and articles (by others) on smallpox vaccinations in a variety of countries.